Guide to the Amy L. Lettick Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Amy L. Lettick papers
1920-1988
MS 1593
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
25.17
(30 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, journals and diaries, audio and video tapes, films, and publications relating to the development and care of an autistic child and the founding of the Benhaven school.
Lettick, Amy L.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Amy L. Lettick, 1990-1992, and 1998, 1999.
Biographical / Historical
Amy L. Lettick was the founder of Benhaven, a private, nonprofit school community in New Haven for autistic and neurologically impaired individuals. Benhaven was founded in 1967 as an outgrowth of Lettick's search for an educational and social program for her autistic son, Benjamin. In 1975, Yale University conferred an honorary doctorate upon Amy Lettick for her work with autistic children and the founding of Benhaven. Lettick died on November 22, 2017 in Tempe, Arizona.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, journals and diaries, audio and video tapes, films, and publications relating to the development and care of an autistic child and the founding of the Benhaven school.
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
Autism; Autistic children; Children with disabilities -- Education; Children with mental disabilities -- Education; Lettick, Amy L.; Benhaven (School)
- Inventory, 1912, 1935, 1937, 1940, 1955-1990, undated; 6 linear feet (6 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Preliminary inventory by Carol King, 1991 May
  Received from: Amy L. Lettick, 1990-1991
  - "Benjamin Lettick, from birth 1955 Apr 7 - 1956 Nov," correspondence and printed material, 1961 Jul, Aug, Oct, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Journal of Amy L. Lettick recording Benjamin Lettick's daily progress, 1961 October 27 - 1967 December 3, 1990 March 9, undated (Box 1, Folder 2-18)
  - Typescript of Amy L. Lettick's journal, entitled "The Daily Records of A 6-Year Educational Program Designed For A Severely Autistic Boy,", 1955-1963, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 19-26)
  - Incomplete original foreword of journal by Sylvia Kottler, 1990 July (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Notebooks containing observations, 1958, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Diaries of Amy L. Lettick, 1935, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, notes and newspaper clipping found in 1937 dairy, 1912, 1937, 1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Photographs of Benjamin Lettick and his family, 1955-1962 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Presentation on learning behavior of the child, by Dr. Newell Kephart at the state convention of the Texas Society for Crippled Children and Adults, 1962 October 26 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - "The Brain Injured Child, and the Slow Learner in the Classroom," class lecture by Newell Kephart, Purdue University, 1963 May 13 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Lecture notes and related material on the care of autistic children, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Benhaven:
    - Correspondence, 1979, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Public relations material pertaining to Benhaven, 1978, 1980-1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Publications:
      - Benhaven's Two Paths Into the Future ,by Amy L. Lettick, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - Benhaven's Way, by Amy L. Lettick, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - An Experimental Training Project for Autistic and neurologically Impaired Children, by David F. Freschi, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - Benhaven Policy Manual, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 40)
      - Staff Orientation Handbook: Benhaven, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 41)
      - Benhaven at Work: May through August 1978, by Amy L. Lettick, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 42)
      - Benhaven Then and Now, by Amy L. Lettick, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      - Benhaven Maunual for Handling Severe Agression and Self-Abuse, by Amy L. Lettick, Daniel H. Davis, Larry Wood, Stephen M. Simonson, and Linda R. Simonson, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 44)
      - Benhaven at Work, Vol. II: January-June 1984, (part 1) by Amy L. Lettick, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 45)
      - Benhaven at Work, Vol. II: January-June 1984 (part 2), by Amy L. Lettick, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 46)
      - The Benhaven Staff Evaluation System, by David F. Freschi, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
      - Sexuality and Social Awareness: A Curriculum for Moderately Autistic and/or Neurologically Impaired Individuals, by Dawn A. Lieberman and Mary Bonyai Melone, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
      - Vocational Education Lesson Cores, by David F. Freschi and Larry Wood, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
      - Correspondence and printed material pertaining to Benhaven Press publications and others, 1976, 1979-1981, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 50)
      - Correspondence and printed material pertaining to Benhaven Press publications and others, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
      - Book buyers card index (cardbox), 1979-1980s (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Color slides of Dedication and Annual Awards Dinner, 1971, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Color slides of Board Dinner, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Visitor's Register, Benhaven, 1968 March 4 - 1974 September 5 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Films:
      - Benjamin Lettick:
        - No. 1, 1963 January 13 (Box 3, Folder 56)
        - No. 2, 1963 Apr, May (Box 3, Folder 56)
        - No. 3, 1963 June 1 (Box 3, Folder 57)
        - Nos. 4-5 (part 1 of 2), 1964 April 21 (Box 3, Folder 58)
        - Nos. 4-5 (part 2 of 2), 1964 April 21 (Box 3, Folder 58)
        - No. 6, 1964 Summer (Box 3, Folder 59)
        - No. 7, [1966?] (Box 3, Folder 59)
        - No. 8, 1965 March 28 (Box 3, Folder 60)
        - No. 9, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 60)
      - Rehabilitation Center (No. 10), 1971 (Box 3, Folder 61)
      - Woodcutting (No. 11), 1972-1973 (Box 3)
      - Resistive Walking (No. 12), 1969 January 14 (Box 3)
      - Gym (social) (No. 13), 1971 (Box 3)
      - Resistive movement, Circa 1969 (Box 3)
      - Unidentified, unnumbered reel (Box 3)
    - Audiocassettes (cardbox):
      - Benjamin Lettick, Paul Roberts (5 tapes), 1969 January 1 - May 12 (Box 3)
      - Benjamin Lettick (10 tapes), 1969 June 13 - 1970 November (Box 3)
      - Benjamin Lettick: McGinness Method/ Word acquisition (1 tape), 1971 April (Box 3)
      - Benhaven's Twentieth Anniversary, New Haven Lawn Club (1 tape), 1987 October 29 (Box 3)
    - Videotapes:
      - Benhaven: Professional Training Videotape Series, 1982-1984
        - Program #1 - Applied Academics: Developing a Functional Curriculum Using Applied Academics and Practical Living Skills (Box 4)
        - Program #2 - Pre-Vocational Training (Box 4)
        - Program #3 - Gross Motor Curriculum (Box 4)
        - Program #4 - Residential Program for Autistic and Neurologically Impaired Individuals (Parts 1 and 2) (Box 4)
        - Program #5 - Residential Program (Box 4)
        - Program #6 - Vocational Work Program (Parts 1 and 2) (Box 4)
        - Program #7 - Vocational and Work Activity Benchwork, Horticultural and Farm Activities (Box 5)
        - Program #8 - Teaching Autistic People How to Play (Box 5)
        - Program #9 - Functional Language (Box 5)
        - Program #10 - (tape not made) (Box 5)
        - Program #11 - Administration of Benhaven's Residential Program (Box 5)
        - Program #12 - A Model for Operating a School/ Vocational Training Program for Autistic Children and Adolescents (Box 5)
        - Program #13 - Untitled, incomplete master (Box 5)
        - Program #14 - Benhaven: Historical Perspective Overview (Box 5)
      - "Amy Lettick on Teaching" (Box 5)
      - Tape #1 - Structuring Learning (Box 6)
      - Tape #2 - Planning a Lesson (Box 6)
      - Tape #3 - Variations on a Task (Box 6)
      - Tape #4 - Kitchen Activities (Box 6)
      - Tape #5 - Housekeeping (Box 6)
      - Tape #6 - Teaching Play, Stringing Beads (Box 6)
      - Tape #7 - Teaching Jigsaw Puzzles (Box 6)
      - Tape #8 - Teaching Ballroom Dancing (Box 6)
      - Tape #9 - Teaching Card Playing (Box 6)
      - Tape #10 - Introduction to Recreation (Box 6)
      - Tape #11 - Goal Setting: Its Form and Function (Parts 1 and 2) (Box 6)
      - Tape #12 - Addressing and Teaching the Autistic (Parts 1 and 2) (Box 6)
      - Benhaven orientation (copy 2), 1978 (Box 6)
      - Update of Yale Benhaven film, interview at end (Part 2), 1978 (Aug) (Box 6)
      - End of Winter Dance, 1987 March 7 (Box 6)
      - Jarrod Law's Dancing class, 1987 Jan, Sep, 1988 June (Box 6)
      - Matt Hochman Keyboard and Dancing; Jarrod Law Doing the Twist, 1989 (Box 6)
- Additional Material, 1953-1991, undated; Accession 1992-M-041; 6.25 linear feet (7 boxes)
  Addition inventory by Carol King 1992 Jul
  Received from: Amy L. Lettick, 1991 Oct 28
  - Correspondence/subject files:
    - Accreditation and licensure, 1967-1974, undated (Box 1)
    - Articles, 1972-1983, undated (Box 1)
    - Autism Society of America (formerly National Society for Autistic Children (NSAC):
      - 1970-1982 (Box 1)
      - 1986-1989, undated (Box 1)
    - Benhaven board dinners (awards), 1972-1987, undated (Box 1)
    - Benhaven brochures, 1967-1986, undated (Box 1)
    - Benhaven correspondence:
      - 1960-1961 (Box 1)
      - 1966-1989 (Box 1)
    - Benhaven twentieth anniversary dinner, 1986-1987, undated (Box 1)
    - Diaries of Amy Lettick, with typed transcriptions, 1953, 1955-1957 (Box 1)
    - Drazen, Beatrice, 1971-1973, undated (Box 1)
    - Eastside, 1972-1977, undated (Box 1)
    - Fenichel, Carl, 1966-1967, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Fund-raising:
      - Dorm Delights, 1982-1984, undated (Box 1)
      - Friends of Benhaven, 1972-1989, n.d (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous, 1967-1977, 1980-1986, undated (Box 1)
      - Probus Club, 1968-1974 (Box 1)
    - Harrison, Ida, 1972-1988, undated (Box 2)
    - Harrison playground, 1987-1989, undated (Box 2)
    - Impact of Benhaven, 1976-1978, undated (Box 2)
    - Jayhaven-Northside, 1971-1973 March-Dec, 1974-1977, undated (Box 2)
    - Jayhaven-Northside: photographs, undated (Box 2)
    - Kephart, Newell C., Purdue University, 1962-1973, undated (Box 2)
    - Legislation: fund raising, 1968-1977, n.d (Box 2)
    - Marks, Nancy Lurie, 1972-1975, 1985, undated (Box 2)
    - Medalie House, 1969-1972, 1983-1986, n.d (Box 2)
    - Olander, Timothy, 1986-1989, undated (Box 2)
    - Oppenheim, Rosalind, 1971, 1982, 1990, undated (Box 2)
    - Parents' apartment, 1982-1983, undated (Box 2)
    - Potter, Moses, 1974 June - 1975 Apr, undated (Box 2)
    - Rimland, Bernard, 1968-1982, 1989-1990, undated (Box 2)
    - Shodell, Margaret, 1966-1967, undated (Box 2)
    - Ten year data:
      - Enrollees, 1975-1989 (Box 2)
      - Medication records, 1977-1983, undated (Box 2)
      - Staff, 1975-1976, 1987, undated (Box 2)
      - Students' general information as a group, 1967-1980, n.d (Box 2)
  - Journal appendix 2: material from Benhaven files
    - Part A: correspondence, instructional material (1 folder), 1962-1969 (Box 2)
    - Part B: tests, evaluations, recommendations (4 folders), 1969-1990 (Box 2)
    - List of contents of appendix 2, part B (compiled by donor) (Box 2)
    - Part C: monthly Benhaven reports (14 folders), 1968-1991 (Box 3)
  - Journal appendix 3:
    - Part A: medical records from Drs. Wessell/LaCamera (1 folder), 1960s-1980s (Box 3)
    - Part B: Yale Child Study Center records (1 folder), 1970-1986 (Box 3)
    - List of contents of appendix 3, parts A, B (compiled by donor) (Box 3)
  - Benjamin Lettick's training sessions and adult activities
    - Typed commentaries on films of training sessions, 1962-1969 (Box 3)
    - Master tape, part 1, 1 (Box 8)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
      - Films of training sessions, 1962-1971
      - Adult activities, 1989-1990
    - Master tape, part 2: Adult activities, Waldbaum's, Seton Name Plate Corp., 1990; 1 (Box 9)
  - Index of subject headings:
    - A - Lettick, Amy (Box 4)
    - Lettick, Amy (cont'd) - Z (Box 5)
  - Index of main entries:
    - A - J (Box 5)
    - K - R (Box 6)
    - S - Z (Box 7)
- Additional Material, Circa 1920s-1992, undated; Accession 1992-M-079; 8.75 linear feet (9 boxes)
  Received from: Amy L. Lettick, 1992 Jun 10
  - Photocopy of original journal:
    - Pages 1-103 (Box 1)
    - Pages 104-205 (Box 1)
    - Pages 206-305 (Box 1)
    - Pages 306-399 (Box 1)
    - Pages 400-483, unnumbered pages (Box 1)
  - Index to journal:
    - Original, drafts 1, 2 (Box 1)
    - Original, drafts 3, 4, 5 (Box 1)
    - "Compiled by author" (Box 1)
  - Benhaven Bulletin, 1972-1988 (Box 1)
  - Benhaven reports on Benjamin Lettick, 1990 March - 1992 April (Box 1)
  - Diaries of Amy Lettick, some transcribed, 1953, 1955-1957, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Benhaven at Work: final draft, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Benhaven Then and Now: final draft, 1979 (Box 1)
  - RSVP radio talk show of, 1971 February 11; 1 (Box 1)
  - Benhaven: printed material and button, undated (Box 1)
  - Personal file:
    General note
    See also: box 5
    - Clippings, memorabilia: school years (2 folders), 1926-1942 (Box 2)
    - Clippings, early years, 1931-1938 (Box 2)
    - Clippings, memorabilia:
      - Dance programs, 1935-1940 (Box 2)
      - Household inventory, 1947 (Box 2)
      - Children's immunization records, 1950-1967 (Box 2)
      - Moving book, 1962 (Box 2)
      - Travel diary, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Clippings, 1949-1991, undated (Box 2)
    - Clippings, miscellaneous:
      - Gift registry, 1942, 1945 (Box 2)
      - Ladin, Harvey, 1978, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Lettick, Birney, 1941, undated (Box 2)
      - Lettick, David, 1963-1965, undated (Box 2)
      - Marshall Journal, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Cohen, Donald, 1980-1992 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1940-1991 (Box 2)
    - Deinstitutionalization, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - Divorce (3 folders), 1974-1987 (Box 2)
    - Internal Revenue, 1983-1984 (Box 2)
    - L, 1947-1949, 1955, undated (Box 2)
    - Lafferty, Perry: radio scripts, 1940 (Box 2)
    - Lettick, Birney, 1942-1980 (Box 2)
    - Recording to Birney Lettick, made by Amy Lettick, 1948 (Box 2)
    - Report cards, transcripts of Amy Lettick, 1936-1942, undated (Box 2)
    - Retirement from Benhaven, 1989-1992 (Box 2)
    - Reviews, rejections (2 folders), 1973-1989 (Box 2)
    - Yale doctorate, University of New Haven, 1973-1988 (Box 2)
  - Writings, 1931-1991 (Box 3)
    See also: box 6
  - Photographs, 1920s-1990s, undated (Box 4)
    - Individuals (Box 4)
    - Family/friends (Box 4)
    - Benhaven/professional (Box 4)
    - Wedding album, 1945 (Box 4)
  - Marsahll Journal: A Daily Record of Life in Milford, Connecticut 1787-179 0, transcription, commentary, and index by A. L. Lettick (4 folders), 1992 (Box 4)
  - Index to personal file (box 2) (Box 5)
  - Index to writings (box 3) (Box 6)
  - Chronological card file of Amy L. Lettick, Benjamin Lettick, and Benhaven--Events/activities:
    - 1905-1971 August (Box 7)
    - 1971 September - 1974 January (Box 8)
    - 1974 February - 1981 (Box 9)
- Additional Material, Accession 1999-M-061
  - Family photographs, 1937, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Ways and Means [by A.L.L.]
    - Gen Bk [draft], Circa 1991 (Box 1)
    - GB [draft], 1990 (Box 1)
    - 1 [draft], 1991 (Box 1)
    - 4 [draft], undated (Box 1)
    - Floppy disk, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Published version, 1998 (Box 1)
  - "Benhaven" [by A.L.L.], Circa 1979 (Box 1)
  - "The Marshall Journal" [photocopy of an original journal, 1787-1790, from Milford, Connecticut, with transcription and commentary by A.L.L.], 1992 (Box 1)
  - "The Chapter Incident" [notes by A.L.L.], undated (Box 1)
  - "Teaching Low-functioning Autistic and Neurologically Impaired Students" [by A.L.L.], post-1993 (Box 1)
  - Non-Resident Family Training Program, Achievement Center for Children [notes and reports on Benjamin Lettick], 1962-1963 (Box 1)
  - Benhaven--reports on Ben's progress:
    - 1992-1997 (Box 1)
    - 1995-1998 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1995 (Box 2)
  - "Ben's Journal" [by A.L.L. ], post-1993 (Box 2)
- Additional Material, Accession 1999-M-085
  - Correspondence, 1994, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Benhaven's Key People, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Follow-up of Autistic Children in Connecticut, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Writings, 1973, 1983, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Writings about Amy Lettick and Benhaven, 1974, 1979 (Box 1)
- Additional material, 1929-2006; Accession 2007-M-033
  - Appointment books, 1994, 1997-2001, 2003-2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Benhaven reports [re: Ben Lettick]
    - 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 2 - 6)
    - 2003-2006 (Box 2, Folder 7 - 10)
  - Biographical [re: Amy Lettick], 2005, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Clippings [re: Amy Lettick], 1992 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1975, 1993-2003, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence [from Beatrice Drazen estate], 1950 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Essays [from Beatrice Drazen estate], undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Photographs, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Photographs [from Beatrice Drazen estate], 1929, 1941, 1945, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Seahaven furnishings appraisal, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Interview of Amy Lettick on the occasion of her 85th birthday [original compact disc; restricted], 2006 June 22 (Box 3)
    Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.